Hello, and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today
we're going to be learning about
how to calculate molar masses.
We're going to be looking at examples of
atoms, molecules, compounds, and hydrates.
We're going to go through the concept
of really what is a molar mass, which is
going to be using your periodic tables
to calculate all these different values.
So this is meant to help introductory
and general chemistry students for how
to do the fundamental skills required
of you to pass general chemistry.
So let's take a look at all
these different examples.
Let's go to the first one and
really how we can do that.
Um, and like I mentioned
earlier, what we're going to
be doing is four molar masses.
Um, what this is, is the mass in
grams, and that's representing one
mole of a particular substance.
So that's for every grams
of, of grams per mole.
Now this could come under many
different names depending on who
your chemistry professor is or who,
uh, you are learning this from.
Sometimes you might see it as other
names like molecular mass, molecular
weight, formula mass, formula weight.
They're all referring to the same general
concept, they might be changing units
depending on really what particular
thing you are referring to, but
they're all using your periodic table.
We're going to be focusing on this first
one, um, but mainly grams per mole and
how to do those types of conversions which
will be required later in your semesters.
For how to do mole conversions.
Let's take a look at our first example.
First example here is let's do
an easy one and just be able
to make sure we understand what
that concept is of molar mass.
So I want to just figure out what the
molar mass of just nitrogen atom is.
So for this one, when you're looking
at your periodic table, you're going
to see the following values here.
When you find nitrogen
or any of your elements.
And there's a couple different
numbers here that are very important.
We have up top, we have the atomic
number, which tells you how many
protons there are, how many electrons
there are for a neutral element.
The number down here is the atomic mass,
which is generally represented in amu.
However, we can directly relate this
to measurements that you do in the
laboratory setting in grams per mole.
So it's a one to one
conversion, so if you have 14.
007 AMU, you also have 14.
007 grams of nitrogen for
every one mole of nitrogen.
So how do you, what
exactly does that mean?
Well, being that I have a single
nitrogen atom here, We can say, hey,
if I have one mole of this, or 6.
022 times 10 to the 23 atoms of
it, then that's going to weigh 14.
007 grams.
So this is what we're going to be doing.
Now, when we have, let's say,
different amounts of compounds, we
got to do a little bit more math here.
Let's take a look at the next
example, and we'll proceedingly get
a little bit harder with each one.
With this example, let's find
the molar mass of oxygen gas.
Well, oxygen gas, whenever someone
mentions like hydrogen, oxygen,
nitrogen, fluorine, iodine, bromine,
chlorine, gas, these are your natural
diatomics, meaning they have a subscript
of two next to each one of them.
So what do we got to do here?
Well, when we are looking at O2,
that tells you that you have two
moles of oxygen within two moles of
oxygen atom in one mole of oxygen
molecule, okay, so O2 molecule.
So it's a conversion term within itself.
So how do, can we
actually do the math here?
Well, earlier, if we looked at
our periodic table, and I grabbed
the value earlier, if we have 15.
99 grams of oxygen atom, well,
we have a subscript of 2 here.
So what we're gonna do to find the
entire molar mass of this is we're
gonna multiply that number by two
because our subscript is two, so
we're going to compensate for that.
Now, this is equivalent to every
one mole of O two molecule.
So when we do that, ma,
that, um, that math here.
What we are going to get from that is 31.
98 grams of O2 for every 1 mole of O2.
So this is our molar mass.
This is how we can do it for
a basic chemical compound.
We're just multiplying our molar
mass from our periodic table.
By the subscripts.
So we're counting the number of atoms.
So we had two oxygen atoms bound,
bound together covalently, and
we're going to be showing that as
well within our calculations too.
So if I were to kind of move on
to a slightly more, a little bit
different one, well here I have ozone.
So ozone is O3.
So what that tells you is that, hey, we
have the subscript right here, and with
that subscript, we have three oxygen
atoms that are in this calculation.
So we need to take that three, multiply it
by the molar mass, so three times, uh, 15.
999 grams per mole, and what that
will get us is a molar mass of 47.
97 grams.
of ozone for every mole of ozone.
Okay.
So this is the idea here that when we
are calculating those molar masses,
we're multiplying it by the subscripts
that we see within the chemical formula.
Let's go to a slightly harder one.
Let's go to the next, but this
next example, our molecules getting
a little bit bigger as we go.
And what we have to do
is the same general idea.
So I have propane gas here, which
you might use for barbecuing or
grilling, or maybe cooking at home.
So propane has three carbons,
eight hydrogens within its formula.
So this is what is going to be counting
for each of these atoms that we have here.
So we can see the three carbons
connected, all the hydrogens
connected to their respective carbon.
So we are going to do our math.
So what we have is three.
Times 12.01 grams per
mole per carbon, right?
And you want to put those different units
here, we'll put that in parentheses.
And what we're gonna do is we're gonna
add that with eight hydrogens times
1.008 grams per mole of hydrogen.
Now when we take all those values
and add them together, what we are
going to get is a total molar mass.
A 44.094 grams of C3H8 for
every one mole of C3H8.
And what this will be used
for is a conversion term.
So if you want to go from grams
to moles within your conversion
or something with propane, this
is what you would use right here.
So this is a conversion term.
And you can go to my other
videos as well to see how that
conversion term can be used.
So the what is a mole video or
other videos as well to help you
be able to use it and to help you
figure out these types of problems.
Let's go on to an even
harder one with parentheses.
Find the molar mass of the
following ionic compound.
So when it's ionic, what we are looking at
is we have a metal bound to a non metal.
So we have our metal here on the left.
And the thing that's different about this
one is notice how we have parentheses.
So what exactly is this doing here?
Well, it's like math
that's being carried out.
We need to make sure we are
counting our atoms properly.
So let's take a look.
So on the left hand side, we
have two aluminums based on
the subscript that is here.
Now inside of this sub of this
parentheses, well, we have a
three that's outside of it.
So what exactly is that going to do?
Well, it's kind of like
an algebra problem.
We're going to be carrying
out the math on the subscripts
that are with inside of this.
So what do I mean by that?
Well, if on inside I have one carbon
atom, we're going to be multiplying
that by, let's say if I make this red,
we're going to be multiplying this
by three for our carbon atoms inside.
So we'll have a total of
three carbon atoms, okay?
Now, oxygen in this case, it had, oxygen
originally had three carbon atoms, and
now we're going to be multiplying it
by another three carbon atoms inside.
So we have a total of nine
oxygens, two aluminum, and
three carbons looking at that.
So we gotta make sure we are
properly showing how we are adding
all these different pieces up when
we are doing our molar masses.
If I'm going to be carrying out the
math, each one of these is going to
be in their own set of parentheses.
So we'll do 2 times 26.
982 grams per mole for aluminum.
We'll do the same thing
for, let's say, for carbon.
So carbon, we have a total of 3 of them,
and we're going to times that by 12.
01 grams per mole of carbon.
And then we'll be adding that to oxygen.
So I'm gonna continue that
on the bottom here and that.
And we have a total of nine
oxygens times 15.99 grams per mole.
Now when we add up all these different
values together, you're gonna get a
pretty big molar mass of, uh, 233.904.
When you go through the mathematics
of this, so it's two, two, three,
three, nine, zero, four grams per mole.
And that's for the entire molecule.
So when we are reporting that,
that means that if you were to go
to a balance, let's say in the lab
setting, and you measure out, uh, 233.
904 grams of aluminum carbonate, Then
that represents one mole of that compound.
So they are equal to each other.
So one mole, Al2, CO3.
So these two terms are equal.
So keep that in mind.
One mole is equal to 233.
904 grams.
of aluminum to carbonate.
So aluminum, carbonate, these two
are equivalent to one another, which
is really important for when you are
doing your calculations to realize
that they are equivalent to each other.
They're a ratio.
They help you be able
to cancel your units.
So if you need to go from moles to mass,
This is what you would have to do every
single time that you do this calculation.
Let's go on to our next one,
which is involving a hydrate.
Find the molar mass of Epsom salt.
So Epsom salt is something you
can buy in a grocery store, or a
dollar store, or a hardware store.
And what this one is, is a hydrate.
Meaning that we have MgSO4,
and I have what looks like a
multiply symbol, and seven waters.
Now, does that mean that you
have to multiply seven waters?
No.
So what this is telling you
is that we have seven waters
patched to our magnesium sulfate.
So they are like little
things surrounding it.
So I have a little magnesium
sulfate over here now.
So what that means is I have seven
waters that are, that are completely.
surrounding this particular molecule here.
So when we want to write this,
we will have these seven little
waters that are completely around
our structure, just like so.
So we're going to take it and count
our atoms just like we did before.
And add up all their molar masses,
each one individually, you do not
want to multiply that the seven waters
times magnesium sulfate, you're going
to be adding seven waters onto this.
So when we are doing our math here, so
the first one, right, if we have our
individual properties, so we have one
magnesium that is in this compound.
So one times 24.
3 grams per mole, and that's for Mg.
We'll then add that to our sulfur, right?
We have 1 sulfur that is in our formula.
So that's 1 times 32.
07 grams per mole.
And then we have our oxygens,
which are in the compound itself.
So we're going to do
that a little separately.
We have 14 times 15.
99 grams per mole for our oxygens.
Okay, so now we have to do
for our water components.
So we are going to add these parts
together, and then we're also
going to add our 7 waters as well.
So, how do we go about that?
Well, we have a coefficient of 7, and
then we had 2 times 2, which is 14.
Multiply that by 1.
008 grams per mole.
We're adding up all
these little pieces here.
It's a lot.
And now we'll have a total of 7 oxygens
that are in this compound times 15.
99 grams per mole.
So that means that overall you have
11 oxygen atoms in this compound, but
we're just separating them between the
water component And the, um, and the
sulf, and the other parts from earlier.
So sulfur.
and then hydrogen.
All right, so now when we have all
these values, we're going to add
them all up to make one big hydrate.
So when we do all the math, we'll take 24.
3 plus 32.
07 plus 4 times 15.
99 Plus 14 times 1.
008 plus 7 times 15.
99.
So when you do that, we will get 246.
372 grams of MgSO4 and 7 waters all
over 1 mole of the same compound.
It is a little bit of a, little
bit of work to do that hydrate.
But it's something that allows you
to really see that hey that this is
not a multiply We need to add these
individual pieces when you're doing
that molar mass Let's do another
one with a bigger covalent molecule.
So these molecules can get really big
and really massive hydrates I think
are the hardest but hopefully this
will help you be able to see that
firsthand for if you have to do for
homework or an exam or Even in a lab
sometimes Let's go to our last example.
All right?
If we wanna calculate the molar mass
of, let's say something like a bio or an
organic molecule, or a biomolecule like
serotonin, which is a neurotransmitter
molecule that's responsible for happiness.
So if you're given a molecule that
looks like the one all the way on, on
the, on the left hand side here, right?
You might have to go through and count
all the individual atoms that are here.
So when we count them all up, What you
would get is that there's 10 carbons, 12
hydrogens, two nitrogens, and one oxygen.
So we gotta go through that entire
process of adding all those up,
just like how we did earlier, by
taking all of them and adding them.
If once again we wanted to find
the molar mass of serotonin,
we can go through that process.
So the first thing we would
do is being that carbon.
We have 10 carbons and each one is 12.01.
grams per mole of carbon.
We then have 12 hydrogens, and that's 1.
008 grams per mole of hydrogen,
and then we have nitrogen.
We have a total of two of them, times 14.
001 grams per mole of nitrogen, and then
we have oxygen, which there are a total of
two of them, or sorry, one of them here.
And that's 15.
99 grams per mole.
So what we will do with all those
little pieces is you're going to
take them and add them all up.
And what you will get for
a final answer is 176.
206 grams of serotonin for
every one mole of serotonin.
Okay, so that's a conversion term that we
can use, um, for these types of problems.
So that if you need to cancel them
out, do your mathematics, now you
know how to do molar masses, so go out
there, go figure out those problems
on your homeworks, on your exams,
and do well in your chemistry course.
I hope that this video helped.
Please hit that like and subscribe
button if it did, and I hope to
see you back for future videos.
Bye now.